<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wordlist on Source material for the Corpus of Historical Mapudungun (CHM)</title>
    <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/tags/wordlist/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Wordlist on Source material for the Corpus of Historical Mapudungun (CHM)</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2021 Benjamín Molineaux</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Feb 1878 16:45:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/tags/wordlist/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Federico Barbará: Manual o vocabulario de la lengua pampa</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/barbara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Feb 1878 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/bonus-texts/barbara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transcribed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is a brief grammar and Spanish-Mapudungun vocabulary focusing on the dialect of the pampas, east of the Andes (Puelmapu), written by Liutenant Colonel Carlos Federico Barbará, of the Argentinian army. The grammatical content follows Febrés (1765) quite closely.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A version of the &lt;em&gt;Vocabulary&lt;/em&gt; can be found at the following website:&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pueblosoriginarios.com/lenguas/pampa.php&#34;&gt;https://pueblosoriginarios.com/lenguas/pampa.php&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;form action=&#34;ValdiviaSermones.pdf&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/1879BarbaraTexts.html&#34; class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;UN-Tagged Text (Web)&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/Barbara.pdf&#34; class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;PDF Text (Image Scans)&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elias Herckmans: Vocabula Chilensia</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/herckmans/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 1643 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/herckmans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transcribed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is a vocabulary of some 515 words and phrases compiled by Dutch explorers and military men on a reconnaissance mission to Chile from their territories in Brazil. The expedition set out in January 1643 with Hendrik Brouwer as its admiral. The vice-admiral was one Elias Herckmans, Governor of Parahyba, who, upon Brouwer&amp;rsquo;s death in August 1643, took over the entire expedition. As the most senior officer on the expedition and chief negotiator with the local population, the vocabulary is attributed to him. The details of the process of elicitation, however, are unclear.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Luis de Valdivia: Arte y Gramática</title>
      <link>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/valdiviagramatica/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 1606 16:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://benmolineaux.github.io/bookshelf/en/core-texts/valdiviagramatica/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Partially Transcribed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is the oldest textual source explicitly focusing on Mapudungun.&#xA;Its author is Father Luis de Valdivia, a Spanish priest who was one of the original members of the Chilean Mission of the Society of Jesus (Jesuits), founded in 1593.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Throughout his stay in the country, Valdivia was actively involved not only in the education of the colonists and evangelisation of the Mapuche, but also in early attempts to prevent military confrontations between the two groups. He travelled widely in the territories, learning and preaching in the language (see de Olivares 2005; Toribio Medina 1894).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
